<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A monument of mortalitie vpon the death and funerals, of the gracious prince, Lodovick, late Duke of Richmond and Lenox: Earle of New-castle, and Darnley, &amp;c. ... By Iames Cleland Doctor in Diuinitie and domestick chaplaine to his Grace.</title>
            <author>Cleland, James, d. 1627.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18977</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5396</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108068</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843757</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843757</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8513</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18977)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8513)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1093:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A monument of mortalitie vpon the death and funerals, of the gracious prince, Lodovick, late Duke of Richmond and Lenox: Earle of New-castle, and Darnley, &amp;c. ... By Iames Cleland Doctor in Diuinitie and domestick chaplaine to his Grace.</title>
                  <author>Cleland, James, d. 1627.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby for Ralph Rounthwaite,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an additional title page, engraved.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Richmond, Ludovic Stuart, --  Duke of, 1574-1624.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8513:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8513:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MONVMENT OF MORTALITIE, VPON THE DEATH AND FVNE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RALS, OF THE GRACIOVS PRINCE, <hi>LODOVICK,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Late Duke of Richmond and Lenox: Earle of New-caſtle, and Darnley, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lord of Torbolton, and Methuen: Baron of <hi>Settrington,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Knight of the Noble Order of the GARTER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lord high Admirall and great Chamberlaine of</hi> SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>Lord high Steward to the Kings moſt Excellent <hi>Majeſties most Honorable Houſe-hold: Gentleman</hi> of his Bed-chamber: and one of his <hi>Majesties moſt Honorable Prini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Councell for ENGLAND and SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Captaine of an hundreth Scots-men at Armes of the</hi> French Kings Ordinances.</p>
            <p>By IAMES CLELAND <hi>Doctor in Diuinitie</hi> and Domeſtick Chaplaine to his GRACE.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>William Stans by</hi> for <hi>Ralph Rounthwaite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8513:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8513:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE IL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LVSTRIOVS PRINCE, ESME, Duke of <hi>Lenox,</hi> Earle of March and Darnley: Lord of AVBIGNY Torbolton Methuen: <hi>Baron of</hi> Settrington, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Knight of the Noble Order of the GARTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honourable LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oe here <hi>A Monument</hi> of mans <hi>Mortalitie,</hi> erected in haſte, to repreſent the <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Funerals,</hi> of my good Lord, your Noble Brother; whoſe heroicke <hi>LIFE</hi> requires more lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:8513:3"/> to build <hi>A MAVSOLE</hi> to his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall Memorie. Meane time J offer vnto your <hi>Grace,</hi> theſe mournefull Spoiles, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Trophees, as moſt proper and due vnto you; his Succeſſour and Jnheritour; in aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance you will accept them fauourably, and with your gracious aſpect, giue them, a ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-power, as the Sunnes reflection did on the Image of <hi>Memnon.</hi> The Ghoſtly vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of his Effigie I know, cannot affright your <hi>Grace,</hi> who is ready and prepared at all howers for Death; nor (I hope) will the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of it, renew your griefe, as <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs</hi> particoloured Coate, cauſed ſorow to his father <hi>Iacob,</hi> and <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſhirt to <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purnia:</hi> But that you will looke and behold in it as <hi>a Mirror</hi> to ſee your <hi>Fate,</hi> as your <hi>Fortune;</hi> and ſo eſteeme me for euer one of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Aprill 20. 1624.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Graces Moſt humbly Deuoted in all dutifull obſeruance, IAMES CLELAND.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:8513:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>IN IVSTA FVNEBRIA, OPTIMI PRINCIPIS, <hi>LODOVICI, Ducis</hi> Richmondiae, <hi>&amp;</hi> Lenoxiae, <hi>&amp;c. EPITAPHIVM.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>Dum Populum, Procereſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuos IACOBVS in vnum</l>
               <l>Cogit, &amp; Europam terror vbi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tenet.</l>
               <l>Spes populi, Procerum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> decus LENOXIVS Heros, </l>
               <l>Non expectato funere raptus obit.</l>
               <l>Prô Superi! non haec mors eſt, ſed Publica clades, </l>
               <l>Quam Rex &amp; Proceres, plebs populuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> lugent.</l>
               <l>Egregiè factum Funus Moeſtiſſma Coniux </l>
               <l>Produxit; Ciniri gloria magna fuit.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="memorial">
            <pb facs="tcp:8513:4"/>
            <head>MONVMENTVM MORTALE, In Obitum Optimi Ducis RICHMONDIAE <hi>&amp;</hi> LENOXIAE, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> B. M. P.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Ide <hi>Mortalis</hi> quiſquis es, hoc te <hi>Monumentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> rogat, ſe vt aſpicias, &amp; Speculum Putes aut Scholam. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iden' formam mutatam, glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am marcidam, euanidam Pompam? Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphus est Mortis, fati Trophaeum, fragilitatis docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum. Diſco omnia praecipits curſu fluere, lubrico or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be verſari, raptari, auolare, vaneſcere. <hi>Fui,</hi> non <hi>ſum:</hi> aut quicquid <hi>Sum</hi> Puluis, cinis, terrae pondus, Parcae ſpolium, dum melior pars mei in caelu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> aſcendit, vnde deſcendit, vbi quieſco, Quis <hi>Fuèrim,</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lubido audire est, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> breus capies. Interim ne mirere quiſquis es, hoc tanto tam<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> inopinato euentu, neue curi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hic cauſas inueſtiga, non vis, non caſus, non ordo eternus fatorum, <hi>Me</hi> de medio; ſed vnus <hi>Ille</hi> Omnium rerum <hi>Moderator</hi> ſuſtulit, vt poſt tot exantla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>os labores, in perpetuum cum eo vinam, ac conquieſcam. Hac moncre volui, nunc abi, ſed heus tu: <hi>Deum Verere, Regem reuerere,</hi> hoc tantum. Vale.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8513:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A Funerall Diſcourſe,</hi> VPON THE DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLORABLE DEATH OF THE GRACIOVS PRINCE, <hi>LODOVICK,</hi> Duke of <hi>Richmond,</hi> and <hi>Lenox, &amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of<note place="margin">Iohn 19. 38.</note> 
                  <hi>Aramathea,</hi> and <hi>Nicodemus</hi> beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of <hi>Pilate</hi> the body of IESVS, and <hi>on the day of preparation,</hi> wrapt it in a fine cleane linnen cloath, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balmed it with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doriferous ſpices, buried it, and ſo gaue him the laſt dutie of Iewiſh Ceremonies, &amp; the firſt of Chriſtian Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8513:5"/> yet <hi>Mary Magdalene,</hi> and the other <hi>Mary,</hi> could not bee ſatisfied with all that was done by <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Nicodemus</hi> for their Lord and Maſter <hi>Chriſt,</hi> vnleſſe in the next day after the Preparation, their poore balme had gone likewiſe for him. After which imitation of theſe two <hi>Maries,</hi> I cannot content my ſelfe with what hath beene done by others hitherto, for my late Lord and Maſter, the Duke of <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> and <hi>Lenox</hi> (though moſt ſufficiently) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept I bring ſome Sindon of my owne now, and buy ſome Balme, to beſtow vpon <hi>his Grace.</hi> Yeſterday you heard how the <hi>Lord Keeper</hi> moſt accuratly and affectionatly expreſſed my <hi>Lord Duke</hi> his <hi>Heroick life:</hi> to day (with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion) I will repreſent vnto you and others afarre off, his <hi>Deplorable Death,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Funerall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Behold them then both in this <hi>Monument,</hi> as better to be conſidered by the Eye, then by the Eare; by the Grauers pencill, then by the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters pen; by ſilence, then by diſcourſe. In this <hi>Monument</hi> which may giue feare to the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, amazement to the Prophane, and ſorrow to all men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For on the ſixteenth day of Februarie laſt, in the Kings Palace of White-Hall, whiles the Kings Majeſtie, the Prince, the Peeres, and the Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Land, were readie to ride in ſtate vnto the High Parliament of England: Behold, an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Statute from the higheſt Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8513:5"/> in Heauen, put in Execution vpon this hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perſon my Lord Duke of Richmond and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nox.</hi> This <hi>Execution</hi> was ſerued vpon him, whiles the people expected a pomp, and whiles I for my part was preparing another <hi>Iacob Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant,</hi> or <hi>King Iames Second Triumphs,</hi> in Executing his Statutes and penal Lawes againſt all Popiſh Policies, and :::::: Practiſes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Majeſties Dominions.</p>
               <p>But, oh, the ſodaine change, and ſtrange paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the peoples expectation, and my deſign; from a glorious <hi>Pompe</hi> on <hi>Horſe-backe,</hi> to a mournfull <hi>Hearſe</hi> followed afoot; from a <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph</hi> to a <hi>Tombe;</hi> from the <hi>Trophees</hi> of ioy, to the <hi>Spoiles</hi> of ſorrow; in a moment, all my thoughts turned to a <hi>Monument.</hi> This is euer the miſerable condition of man, to mixe ſowre with ſweet, or elſe to ioyne them ſo inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably together as a concaue ſuperficies with a conuexe.</p>
               <p>In that morning all the Court, and Citie of <hi>London</hi> were full of mirth, but about noone all in mourning; then in pleaſure and delight, ſoone after in ſorrow and ſadneſſe. Thus the cleareſt dayes haue their ſtormes, the euening is not anſwerable to the calmneſſe of the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, nor to the cleerneſſe of the noone-day, but the Sunne eclipſes, the Cloudes ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt, and the Day is changed into Night, or darkneſſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Statute</hi> that was <hi>Executed</hi> ſo perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8513:6"/> vpon this honourable Perſon was firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted in the vpper Houſe of Parliament in Heauen, generally againſt all men; <hi>All men</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>must once die;</hi> and then receiued, and reſolued vpon of all in the lower Houſe of Parliament on Earth. Here, <hi>Gods Word, Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,</hi> the three States of our Earthly Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, haue ratified and confirmed it, <hi>vna voce,</hi> without appeale.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God</hi> ſaid expreſſely, <hi>In that day wherein thou</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>eateſt of the tree of knowledge of good and euill, thou ſhalt die.</hi> Though Satan, a lyar from the beginning, ſaid to the Woman, <hi>Non omnino</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>moriemini,</hi> Yee ſhall not die at all; and our Mother <hi>Eue</hi> minced the matter, with <hi>ne fortè</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. v. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>moriamini, leſt perchance yee die;</hi> yet Gods ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence paſſed vpon her, and her huſband <hi>Adam,</hi> and all their poſteritie neuer to be repealed, or reuerſed. <hi>Duſt thou art, and to duſt thou ſhalt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. v. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>againe.</hi> As <hi>Leui</hi> was in the loines of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 7. 5.</note> when he payed tithe or tribute, ſo were wee in the loines of <hi>Adam,</hi> when hee did eate of the forbidden Tree; his diſobedience is in vs vnexcuſable, the doome and puniſhment of Death due vnto vs irreuocable, and all of vs, of what eſtate, age or degree ſoeuer wee be, are (without ſome rare and extraordinarie diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, as that of <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> was) liable vnto the ſame. <hi>We muſt needs Die,</hi> ſaid the wiſe<note place="margin">2. Sam. 14. 14.</note> woman of <hi>Tecoah</hi> to <hi>Dauid:</hi> You a Soueraigne and I a Subiect, you a man and I a woman,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8513:6"/> 
                  <hi>Wee must needs die, and are as water ſpilt on the ground. Dauid</hi> confeſſed ſo much on his Death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, <hi>I muſt goe the way of all the earth.</hi> Which<note place="margin">1. Reg. 2. 2.</note> the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> expoundeth with a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold<note place="margin">Ieremie c.</note> exclamation, or terrible acclamation, <hi>O Earth, Earth, Earth, heare the Word of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee muſt haue eares to heare them of men, but our eyes only will heare that of God. Wee vnderſtand him in ſeeing theſe great and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible accidents vnawares to vs. <hi>Earth</hi> which commeſt from <hi>Earth: Earth</hi> which art fed with <hi>Earth: Earth</hi> which remaineſt on <hi>Earth: Earth</hi> which goes to <hi>Earth: Earth</hi> in thy birth, in thy life, and in thy end, behold a Great Man of the Earth returnes to <hi>Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Emperours, Kings,</hi> and <hi>Princes,</hi> you are but <hi>dust,</hi> know it; your Crownes and Scepters de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend of God, acknowledge it: your bodie is but of clay, thinke and ſay it, and therefore you muſt needs breake, and bee diſſolued. Say <hi>Prince,</hi> ſay peſant, ſay rich, ſay poore, ſay all and one, with holy <hi>Iob. Corruption thou art my</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 17. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>father, rottenneſſe thou art my mother,</hi> Wormes and Vermine yee are my brethren and ſiſters, ſay, graue thou art my bed, ſheete thou art my ſhrine, earth thou art my couer, greene graſſe thou art my carpet, ſay Death demand thy due, for thy ſeizure is without ſurrender; and from thy decree there is no appeale. It is not the <hi>Maieſtie</hi> of the <hi>Prince,</hi> or holineſſe of the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> ſtrength of bodie, feature of face, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8513:7"/> riches, honour, or any ſecular regard can pleade againſt Death, or priuiledge any perſon from the Graue. <hi>Nereus</hi> the faire, <hi>Therſites</hi> the foule; <hi>Pyrrhius</hi> the Cooke, <hi>Agamemnon</hi> the King, <hi>Abſalon</hi> with his beautie, and <hi>Lazdrus</hi> with his blaines, muſt once Die. For <hi>Statutum eſt, it is appointed all once to Die.</hi> Heb. 9. 27.</p>
               <p>It is not eminency of <hi>Office,</hi> or <hi>Dignitie</hi> can priuiledge thee: for <hi>Dauid</hi> who was a King<note place="margin">Pſ. 82. 6.</note> himſelfe, a Prophet, and a man after Gods owne heart, ſetteth men as high as they may goe, <hi>I haue ſaid yee are Gods (nuncupatiuè</hi> not <hi>ſubſtantiuè</hi>) and <hi>the children of the moſt high.</hi> This is mans aduancement. But hee bringeth them as lowe, and hath <hi>But</hi> for them, <hi>But yee ſhall Die like men:</hi> and yee Princes, and Great Ones ſhall fall like others; here is his abaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment where the names of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> here ſhew their great difference. <hi>God</hi> ſignifies force ſupport, and the foundation of all; but <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> imbecillitie, infirmitie, and ſo feeble a thing, as it cannot ſtand of it ſelfe: mortall and Diuine are oppoſite and contraries. <hi>God</hi> who made the World at firſt of nothing can marre the<note place="margin">Iſa. 40. 23.</note> greateſt in a moment: <hi>hee bringeth Potentates to nothing, and maketh the Iudges of the earth as vanitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not the ſtrength or ſtatelineſſe of any Place, Palace, or Territorie, Towne-gates, Guardes, or Royall Armies can protect thee from Death. For, <hi>pale Death knocketh with the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Horat.</note>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:8513:7"/> 
                  <hi>ſame fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te</hi> at the Palaces of Princes, as well as at the Cortages of Clownes; if it enter not at<note place="margin">Ier. 9. 3.</note> the gates with full force, it will aſcend by the windowes with great feare. And wee ſee that wiſe men Die as well as fooles, rich Die as well as poore, Noblemen as well as vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar or ignoble, in a word, the good and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men as well as wicked and prophane. For,<note place="margin">Pſ. 89. 47.</note> 
                  <hi>what man is hee that liueth, and ſhall not ſee Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, as no height of honour or eſtimation can priuiledge thee, no ſafety and ſweetneſſe of place protect thee; ſo no power or policie can preſerue thee from the fatall dart of Death. The <hi>King cannot ſaue himſelfe by the multitude of his</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal. 33. 15.</hi> Paul. Iouius de vit. Tamberl. Q. Curc. in vit. Alex.</note> 
                  <hi>hoſt. Tamberlaine,</hi> the terrour of the world, Died with three fits of an Ague, as <hi>Paulus Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius</hi> writeth. <hi>Alexander</hi> that famous Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, acknowledged in his owne perſon this humane frailtie, when in the Olympike Games falling in the duſt, and perceiuing therein the length of his body, hee confeſſed with griefe that ſeuen foote of ground were ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to make him a graue. Death onely,<note place="margin">Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enal.</note> (<hi>Mors ſola fatetur</hi>) ſheweth how bigge mens bodies are.</p>
               <p>Wherefore bee our dayes neuer ſo few, or our yeeres neuer ſo full, reſolue wee muſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Gods Word, Wee muſt all once Die,</hi> whereſoeuer, or what ſtate ſoeuer wee be, no reſiſting, God alone can ſay, <hi>Sum qui ſum, I</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 3. 14.</note>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:8513:8"/> 
                  <hi>am that I am;</hi> and will bee what I haue beene.<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> Men can ſay nothing elſe, but <hi>I am</hi> and <hi>ſhall not be.</hi> Witneſſe this the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> ſong of three parts; Wherein the Elders ſang, We haue beene ſtrong and are not now; The Youth replied, Wee ſhall be ſtrong but are not yet; The Middle-aged ſang, Wee are now ſtrong but ſhall not be. What ſhall I ſay more? All mankind muſt needs ſing this: <hi>Aut ſumus, aut fuimus, aut poſſumus eſſe quod hic est:</hi> Wee are, or haue beene, or may ſoone be, ſuch as this <hi>Our mournfull Obiect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſon,</hi> proueth the ſame, as <hi>Plato in Timaeo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plat. in Tim. De Orthodox. fidei de longit. &amp; breu vitae. Ariſt. Phyſic.</note> 
                  <hi>Euery thing that is compoſed muſt be diſſolued.</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcen, <hi>Euery thing that is made, is ſubiect to be mard. Ariſtotle</hi> holdeth, that euery bodie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of contrarie elements, diſpoſed into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie humours, muſt at length haue a naturall date of corruption. Man is thus, who as hee is the King and Maſter of all things ſublunaries, ſo is hee the moſt mixed and compoſed of all creatures. For hee is made of an immortall ſoule, and corruptible bodie ſubiect to Death; his ſoule aſcendeth from whence it came, his bodie boweth and bendeth downewards: the bodie is compoſed of foure contrarie elements, which in him are ſtill at Deadly warres daily: his ſoule hath a bright, cleare, neate wit, and vnderſtanding in it; ſo hath it a blinde will, and foule affections: the one part of his ſoule is reaſonable, the other part altogether brutiſh
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8513:8"/> and full of ſenſualitie; ſo that Man by <hi>Reaſon</hi> of the Philoſophers, <hi>must Die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, what ſaith <hi>Nature?</hi> is there a <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur?</hi> there muſt bee a <hi>corrumpitur;</hi> euery <hi>oritur</hi> muſt haue a <hi>moritur;</hi> is there an <hi>intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itus,</hi> there muſt bee an <hi>interitus;</hi> euery begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning muſt haue an ending. Wee receiue a life of <hi>Nature,</hi> to render it; wee enter into a life, to goe out of it. There is not an <hi>intrat</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an <hi>exit</hi> in this life's <hi>Tragedie;</hi> a very <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedie</hi> (I ſay) for the moſt part, becauſe wee are all borne crying, wee crie dying; wee come in with moane, and goe out with a groane; let life haue leaue to flaunt and braue it a while on the Stage of the world, yet all but a flouriſh, all is but a flaſh, Death ſtill playes <hi>Rex,</hi> ſtrikes all the Actors, one after one, with a mortall blow; there may bee a little mirth in the middeſt, but Death at the laſt ſtrongly ſteps vp and grim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comes in with a terrible <hi>Epilogue,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes all, and Death makes an end, ſo Death in the end is the end of the <hi>Play;</hi> for <hi>wee muſt all Die. God</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> are agreed vpon the point, her dutifull ſubmiſſion to his Imperious <hi>Muſt,</hi> muſt needes make all men mortall, <hi>all men Die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All, both good and bad are <hi>Actors</hi> on this ſtage of <hi>Mortalitie,</hi> euery one acting a part (as I haue ſaid) ſome of leſſe, ſome of greater dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie; and the Play being ended <hi>Exeunt omnes,</hi> euery one goes off the ſtage, and as Cheſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8513:9"/> without difference they are ſwept from the table of this World, wherein one was a <hi>King,</hi> another a <hi>Queene,</hi> a third a <hi>Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Knight</hi> into Earths bagge; onely this diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction being betwixt good and bad, that the good are <hi>Actors</hi> of a <hi>Comedie;</hi> and howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they beginne, they end merrily: but the bad, are <hi>Actors</hi> of a <hi>Tragedie,</hi> and howſoeuer they beginne, or proceed, yet their end miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, their <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> lamentable. And to conclude this point, <hi>as the tree falleth, ſo it lieth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11. 3.</note> On euery mans particular Death, his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar iudgement attendeth, either of the ſoules eternall bliſſe in heauen, or euerlaſting woe in hell, which all the praiſes, prayers, and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of men, Saints, or Angels cannot reuerſe.</p>
               <p>A conſideration by the miſcreant Atheiſt much contemned, by the temporizing Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian greatly neglected, by the carnall Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ſlightly regarded by the <hi>Popes</hi> pardon pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſing, and pickpurſe-Purgatorie beleeuing Papiſt corruptly entertained, and by very few of the beſt Profeſſors ſo ſincerely and ſeriouſly thought on and embraced, as it ought to bee. For it is the great fault, not onely of great men, whoſe greatneſſe maketh them too often for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfull of goodneſſe, but euen of vs all, high and lowe, rich and poore, great and ſmall, that wee neuer thinke on Death, or prepare to Die, till wee finde and feele wee can no longer liue. Yea wee ſo embrace, admire, adore, and dote
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8513:9"/> vpon this glittering World, and are ſo loath to leaue the ruinous Tabernacle of our corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible fleſh, that wee are not content or willing to goe to heauen, till wee ſee there is no reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, wee can ſtay no longer on earth: yet <hi>Die must all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Experience,</hi> likewiſe teacheth vs we muſt all <hi>Die,</hi> to day our Superiours, to morrow our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours, euen now our equals Die while wee are liuing. Looke aboue vs, belowe, within, without, and round about vs, all tell vs wee <hi>muſt all once Die.</hi> Conſider we the things that are about vs, wee ſhall ſee the apparell on our backes, made of the wooll of beaſts, that are Dead, the ſilke wee weare, wrought by worms which Died in the worke, the gloues on our hands, the ſhooes on our feet, the skinnes of Sheepe or Neat, who loſt their liues to couer our nakedneſſe. The meate on our tables, the members of creatures that haue died to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine our liues. But what neede haue wee of theſe demonſtrations, and reſemblances to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince vs of our <hi>Mortalitie?</hi> ſince we haue both a continuall ſight of it in others, in our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, brethren, kinsfolke, neighbours, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, which are gone the way of <hi>all fleſh</hi> before vs: and alſo a daily ſenſe of it in our ſelues by the aches of our bones, heauineſſe of our bodies, dimneſſe of our eyes, deafneſſe of our eares, trembling of our hands, baldneſſe of our heads, grayneſſe of our haires, that very
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8513:10"/> ſhortly wee muſt follow after them. Nay, doe wee not conſider that our eyes euery night Die to ſleepe to ſhew vs in laſt wee muſt ſleepe in Death: the haire of our heads, the nailes of our fingers calling ſo often for polling and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, tell vs that the whole body muſt ſhortly be ſhaued by Death. Our ſtomacke ſtill dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting our meate, and crauing for more, ſheweth vs the inſatiable manner of the graue, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing eaten and digeſted our Anceſters, gapeth for vs, and when it hath deuoured vs, will hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger alſo for our Succeſſours The wormes take poſſeſſion of vs, almoſt as ſoone as wee doe of life, and haue beſpoken vs euen in our cradles, for their fellowes that await vs on earth.</p>
               <p>Thus Death is alreadie in vs and on vs, wee it on our faces by wrinkles; wee beare it in our browes, whoſe furrowes are the emblemes of the Graue; wee put it on our backes in our clothes, and are clad in Death from top to toe; wee cramme it in our mouthes with our meate; wee haue it in our bones; wee carrie the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of it in our bowels: ſhew me where Death is not? yet alas, the Deuill doth deaſe vs, the World doth ſo blinde vs, and the ſenſualitie of the Fleſh maketh vs ſo extremely ſenſeleſſe, that we neither heare, nor ſee, nor feele, what lieth ſo heauie vpon vs. If wee be young, wee feare not Death at our backes; if ſicke, wee feele not Death treading on our heeles; if old, we looke aſquint and ſee not Death before our
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8513:10"/> eyes: ſuch is our dulneſſe that neither <hi>Gods Word, Reaſon,</hi> nor <hi>Experience</hi> can teach vs, <hi>We must all once die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt proofe of thoſe three teſtimonies on earth, ſhould perſwade al thoſe who beleeue in God; the ſecond, thoſe who follow the light of Nature; the third, all ſort of people. Though we had neither <hi>Reaſon,</hi> nor <hi>Experience</hi> to tell vs, <hi>Wee muſt die,</hi> yet <hi>Gods Word</hi> is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to euince it: though the <hi>Word of God</hi> proued it not, yet <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Experience</hi> would force vs to beleeue it: though we had neither the one, nor the other, of <hi>Gods Word,</hi> and <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Experience</hi> alone were enough to open all mens eyes in the World, good or bad, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or vnfaithful, wiſe or fooles, <hi>We muſt all dye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How euident then this <hi>Statute</hi> is you may eaſily obſerue by theſe three cleere lights of the World, whereof euery one of them apart, or by it ſelfe is more then ſufficient to proue this ſentence, <hi>We must all once die.</hi> Whereof the firſt ſheweth vnto the vnderſtanding, things that are aboue Nature, and begetteth faith in it: the ſecond, naturall things and aboue the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and giue vnto them knowledge: the third, which is <hi>Experience,</hi> the Miſtris of Fooles aſwell as of wiſemen, ſheweth vnto the ſenſes things that are vnder <hi>Reaſon</hi> and imprint in them a feeling. A man that cannot, nor will not learne by theſe three Arguments, <hi>Wee muſt all once die,</hi> hee is a Pagan among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8513:11"/> a beaſt among men, a Dead man among the Liuing.</p>
               <p>Nay the verie <hi>Heathen</hi> or <hi>Infidels</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues<note place="margin">Pier. in hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliph. lib. 45. pag. 470. Coel. Rhod. lib. 11. c. 19. Lactant. l. 2. de diuin. Inſtit. de tribus Parcis. Fuſius Euſeb. lib. 6. de praepar. Euang.</note> acknowledge this Leſſon by their <hi>Poets,</hi> who painted out vnto them three <hi>Deſtinies</hi> or <hi>Goddeſſes, Clothe, Lacheſis, Atropos,</hi> and haue fained tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at the birth of men, they doe ſpinne the life of euerie one, and limit their daies, cutting off their courſe when they pleaſe, either in the beginning or in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt without any hope of returne. Thoſe three are called <hi>Parcae</hi> in <hi>Latine,</hi> by an <hi>Antiphraſis,</hi> or contrarie ſpeech, becauſe they ſpare no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: or elſe, according to the opinion of <hi>Varro</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aul. Gell. lib.</note> in <hi>A. Gellius,</hi> from this Latine word <hi>Partus,</hi> that is to ſay, child-birth. For as <hi>Fulgentius</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Mythologick,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſignifieth calling forth, is ſhe that bringeth the childe out of the Mothers wombe: whoſe ſudden <hi>Lache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> which is lot or hazard receiueth the child, and drawes the threed of its Life: as <hi>Atropos</hi> in an inſtant cutteth the threed of Life without Order, Reaſon, or Law; which made <hi>Plato</hi> call Death <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, inexorable, or inflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. So that you ſee by the verie Pagan Poets, our Life is but a bottome of threed, which the three Deſtinies winde in their hands to diſpoſe of our Life freely thus.</p>
               <q>Clotho colum bajulat, Lacheſis trahit, Atro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos occat.</q>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:8513:11"/>
               <p>Our daies cannot bee long depending alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of a little weake vntwiſted threed, <hi>tenui</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ouid.</note> 
                  <hi>pendentia filo;</hi> and are ſtill in running like a round bottome or a ball.</p>
               <p>So the Heathen Authors imagine to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues a <hi>Phantome</hi> of bare bones without skin or fleſh, hauing a <hi>Crowne</hi> on its head, a <hi>Syth</hi> in one hand, and an <hi>Houre-glaſſe</hi> in the other; thereby to repreſent the Empire, Power, and effects of <hi>Death,</hi> ouer all the Vniuerſe vnder the Heauen; eſpecially ouer <hi>Kings, Princes,</hi> and <hi>Potentates</hi> of the World.</p>
               <p>To this <hi>Crowne</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> appertaines that<note place="margin">Hieron. ad Euſtoch.</note> degrading of perſons, whereof Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> ſpeakes to <hi>Euſtochium, You know not in what time or age Croeſus beganne to obey? At what houre Hecuba, or Darius his Mother?</hi> And this <hi>Ciuill Death</hi> of <hi>ſeruitude</hi> is harder, and more painfull, then <hi>Naturall Death;</hi> and it may bee applied that the Prophet <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw in his Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.<note place="margin">Apoc. 9. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>And in thoſe dayes ſhall men ſeeke Death, and ſhall not find it, and ſhall deſire to Die, and Death ſhall flie from them.</hi> Or the <hi>Crowne,</hi> is to ſignifie, that Death <hi>Crowneth</hi> the Dead: as <hi>Haniball</hi> gaue a <hi>Crowne</hi> to the bodie of <hi>Marſellus, Cleomenes</hi> to <hi>Lidias, Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> to <hi>Paralas, Auguſtus</hi> Crowned <hi>Alexanders Monuments,</hi> the <hi>Vrne</hi> of <hi>Demetrius</hi> his Aſhes was <hi>Crowned;</hi> and when as the Emperor <hi>Adrian</hi> demanded the reaſon from the Philoſopher <hi>Epictetus,</hi> he vnderſtood that thoſe Crownes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8513:12"/> did belong to the Dead as Victors ouer Life,<note place="margin">Iob 7. 1.</note> which is but a perpetuall Warfare.</p>
               <p>Neuer <hi>Monument,</hi> or <hi>Tombe</hi> deſerued bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to bee crowned then this of our <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Gracious Prince, Lodouick,</hi> who hath crowned all the actions of his Life with immortall <hi>Crownes</hi> of glorie and reputation. Though we ſhould giue him as many as they did number in <hi>Ptolomies</hi> pompe, and at <hi>Scillas</hi> Funerall, or as many as <hi>Nero</hi> dedicated to <hi>Iupiter Capitolinus,</hi> like vnto thoſe which <hi>Greece</hi> preſented vnto <hi>Berenice</hi> vpon Golden <hi>Chariots,</hi> yet they ſhould not equall his Merits now after his <hi>Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deaths Sythe</hi> ſignifieth, <hi>All fleſh is graſſe and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 40. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>the beautie and gracet hereof is as a flowre;</hi> and ſo ſoone as the <hi>Sythe</hi> moweth, or cutteth downe all the graſſe in the Medow, it ſpareth none, nor makes any difference, or inequalitie, but cuts downe all alike. If any thing bee more ſeemely, more amiable, more goodly, more gracious, more glorious, in man it is but as a flowre, which though it be more faire in ſhew, and more fragrant in ſmell then graſſe, yet as graſſe withereth, ſo the flowre fadeth: Euen ſo, the greateſt power, pompe, authoritie, eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and moſt illuſtrious eſtate of man, is cut downe and decayeth.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Houre-glaſſe</hi> in <hi>Deaths left hand,</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how much of our life is ſpent, how that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth is in a continuall running, and there is no ſtay of it. How long ſoeuer mans Life be,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8513:12"/> he hath properly but one houre, which thruſts forth his laſt gaſpe is his houre; all the reſt is no more his. Whatſoeuer he hath done in his life is conſidered by this laſt houre, the iudge of all his other houres, the moſt difficult of mans Life. He that is Author of the firſt and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth of the laſt, doth onely know it, foreſees and mockes at man who thinkes hee is farre from it. Before the laſt ſand of this laſt houre be runne, he cannot Crowne his felicitie: We muſt praiſe ſafely after dangers, Nauigation in the Port, and Victorie in Triumph. Who can commend his Life and hold himſelfe ſo happy, whiles that the time paſt miniſters vnto him matter to lament, and that which is to come, to feare? This <hi>My Lords houre</hi> was feared of all his Friends, Seruants, and Followers, yet not expected of any: Euery man did appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it as a change of his condition, but for that they held it to be a farre off, the opinion of the length of time did moderate the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and the leſſe it was foreſeene, the more fearefull hath proued.</p>
               <p>Our Chriſtian Doctrine and pure Religion, terme thoſe <hi>Fates, Deſtinies, Phantomes,</hi> and <hi>Fictions</hi> of the <hi>Poets, A Diſpoſition of Diuine Prouidence concerning mans Life and Death.</hi> So that neither Comfort nor Bleſſing, Croſſe, nor Curſe can come vnto vs, but <hi>by Gods Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> and fore-ſight: not a <hi>haire of our heads can be diminiſhed, nor a cubit cannot be added vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8513:13"/> our ſtature,</hi> without the <hi>Prouidence</hi> of our heauenly Father. It is neither Conſtellation of Starres, influence of the Celeſtiall bodies, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions of Planets, nor any ſuch notionall fantaſie of an Aſtrologicall braine, that can worke our weale or woe, our Life or Death: but it is <hi>God</hi> that ſeeth all, and his <hi>Prouidence</hi> that diſpoſeth. Whoſe diſpoſition being eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and innumerable, as being in the Spirit of God, doth not impoſe any neceſſitie, and in that ſhe carrieth her effects into things that are humane and created, ſhe is temporall, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and contingent. So as man being conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as temporall, he is vnder <hi>Deſtinie,</hi> but in his principall part, which is immortall, he is not ſubiect vnleſſe hee liſt. The action of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinie, vpon the matter is neceſſarie, the effect is not. As the great God, who is the iudge of Life and Death, hath diſpoſed of the life of this <hi>great Duke,</hi> by ſo fatall and mournfull Death, to the end, al that depend on <hi>Princes,</hi> ſhould know they be the effects of his great Iuſtice, and that they <hi>put not their truſt in Princes: nor in the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 146. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Sonne of man, in whom there is no helpe,</hi> or elſe to ſhew that the World and all her greatneſſe are but a ſhadow, duſt, and a puffe of winde.</p>
               <p>Now, ſeeing we haue beene euery way ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently taught, by <hi>Gods Word, Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience;</hi> by the <hi>Ancient</hi> and <hi>Prophane Poets,</hi> and <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> that there is no ſure reſt or
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8513:13"/> reſidence for vs in this World, and that heere we haue no <hi>continuing Citie,</hi> but liue euery day and houre in ſuch vncertaintie, that the higheſt, healthieſt, holieſt, happieſt among men, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not promiſe to themſelues to morrow, let vs eſteeme of euery preſent day, as the day of our Death, and make ſuch a conſcience of all our Wayes, Words, and Workes, as if we were preſently, to giue an account of our life. Hee that thinketh alwayes of Dying, will bee cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect in his doing. The Meditation of Death is a Chriſtian mans Philoſophie, and rightly vſed may well bee termed <hi>mentis dita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio,</hi> the enriching of the mind O let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as carefull Chriſtians, be continually exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in this ſtudie; and as cheerefull and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Profeſſors, bee alwayes buſied in perfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ming thoſe righteous, and religious duties, which wee would doe if wee were Dying: and becauſe that Death in all <hi>places</hi> wayteth for vs, let vs expect it euerie houre, ſuſpect it euerie where, and be at all times prepared for it.</p>
               <p>Eſpecially at this time, let the dreadfull ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle of <hi>Death</hi> before our eyes in this my <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument,</hi> be as a ſhrill Trumpet, ſounding aloud that meſſage of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to <hi>Ezechiah</hi> in our eares, that it may ſinke deepe in our hearts. <hi>Set thy</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 38 1.</note> 
                  <hi>houſe in order, for thou muſt Dye, and ſhall not liue.</hi> Diſpoſe of thy temporall affaires, leaue not thy Lands intangled, thy ſubſtance inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, to be a cauſe of variance to thy poſteritie,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8513:14"/> make thy Will, doe it in time, whileſt thy thoughts are free, thine affections ſtayed, and thy Reaſon not diſtracted with feare, or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes diſturbed with paines, ſo ſhall thy Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be <hi>teſtatio mentis,</hi> a witneſſe of thy mind. Whereas on the contrarie, if thou put ouer the diſpoſing of thine eſtate to that trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome time of ſickneſſes, when thine head aketh, hand ſhaketh, thy tongue faultereth, thine heart fainteth, and euery part is pained, it may iuſtly bee feared, that neither thy words or writing will ſo expreſſe thy meaning, but that thou ſhalt be eaſily drawne to make a Will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter anothers minde, rather then thine owne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Death</hi> hath a thouſand Diſeaſes to kill vs by, which made the Cabaliſt <hi>Rabbins</hi> obſerue nine hundred and ſeuen ſorts of naturall Deaths vpon this Verſe of <hi>Dauid, Vnto God the Lord</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 68. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>belong the iſſues of Death,</hi> not counting the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of violent Deaths by which a man may Dye. And to ſpeake apparantly to truth, there is a greater number of Deadly Diſeaſes and ſickneſſes in a man then there are Bones, Veines, Sinewes, Muſcles, Arteries, Tennons, and all the parts of a Mans bodie. Cut vp an Anatomie, and conſider euery parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular part of mans bodie, and you ſhall not ſeeke nor find one ioynt free from the darts of Death. She can kill vs in the Head by an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexie, by a Syncope; in the Eyes by blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Ophthalmies, and Suffuſions; in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8513:14"/> Eares by deafenſſe, and runnings; in the Noſe by bleeding, in the Mouth by Cankers; in the Tongue by Swelling and Vlcers; in the Throat by Angines and Squinances; in the Stomacke by rawneſſe and coldneſſe; in the Liuer with obſtructions; the Spleene with hardneſſe; in the Belly or Bowels, with the Collicke; in the Kidnies with grauell; in the heart with bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings or pantings; in the Sides with Pleuriſies; in the Hands, in the Feet and Toes, with the Gowt, Knots, and Crampes. To conclude our whole Bodie, and Members are ſeized on by theſe ordinary Diſeaſes, and ſuch.</p>
               <p>Beſides a ſudden <hi>Death</hi> may ſeize on you: you may <hi>Dye in ſleeping,</hi> or in <hi>ſounding,</hi> or <hi>fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> as we ſee daily infinite Examples. A man may bee murthered in the field as <hi>Abell</hi> was:<note place="margin">Gen. 4. 8.</note> a man may fall backward ſitting quietly in his<note place="margin">1. Sam. 4. 48.</note> Chaire, and breake his necke, as <hi>Ely</hi> did: or<note place="margin">Iſa. 37. 37.</note> Die in the Temple as <hi>Senacherib:</hi> or at the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar as <hi>Ioab.</hi> While <hi>Iobs</hi> Sonnes were feaſting,<note place="margin">1. Reg. 2. 34.</note> the houſe fell vpon them: While the ſcoffing Boyes were mocking of Gods Prophet, <hi>Beares</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Reg. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>came from the Wilderneſſe and deuoured them:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 16. 31.</note> When <hi>Corah</hi> and his company were conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, the Earth opened and ſwallowed them. In a word, all our Life is but a Conſumption vnto Death; ſorrowes of minde, and ſick neſſes of the bodie, are but the Harbengers of the graue. Search the Goſpell you ſhall finde one blind, another deafe, the third lame: One
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8513:15"/> 
                  <hi>Lazar</hi> lying at <hi>Diues</hi> gate, another at the <hi>Poole</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 16. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>of Betheſda,</hi> a third at the beautifull gate of the Temple: you ſhall find, heere a <hi>Leper</hi> crying, there a woman with an Iſſue of Bloud adoring. Here the houſe vntiled by the ſick of the Palſie: there the Graues haunted by men poſſeſſed of Deuils. <hi>We cannot</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine) tell what to call our life; whether a Dying life, or a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Death, when euery day our houſes of clay doe cramble to corruption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Set therefore thine houſe in order now, that thy ſoule bee not wearied, when thou art at Deaths doore, or on thy Death-bed, with ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar affaires. Yea, ſet thine heart in order alſo, and forth-with diſpoſe of thy ſoule to caſt vp her reckonings; turne thy ſelfe as <hi>Ezekiah</hi> did to the Wall, that is, from the World to <hi>God.</hi> Conſider what thou haſt beene, examine thy ſelfe what thou art, premeditate what thou ſhalt be. Thinke on thy naked Natiuitie, and bluſh for ſhame; ſigh for griefe on Deaths ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching tyrannie, and tremble for feare, or rather that thou mayeſt bee freed from feare, griefe, and ſhame. <hi>Weepe</hi> as <hi>Ezekiah</hi> did, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayle thy ſinnes paſt, keepe a narrow watch<note place="margin">2. Reg. 20 3. Pſal. 126.</note> ouer thine heart for the time to come. <hi>Sow in teares that thou mayſt reape in ioy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, (not to leaue ſo good a patterne in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny point vnfollowed, which, no doubt, was practized by this our <hi>Prince</hi>) pray too, as <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> did, though thou canſt not in the ſame
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8513:15"/> manner. <hi>Lord remember how I haue walked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee in ſynceritie and truth;</hi> yet to the ſame effect, for mercie, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did. <hi>Lord, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 25. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>not the ſinnes of my youth.</hi> And as Saint <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amb. in Pſal. 38.</note> did. Lord, forgiue mee my faults heere where I haue ſinned, for elſe-where I cannot be releeued, except I haue my pardon heere, it is in vaine to expect the reſtfull comfort of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe hereafter. <hi>Now is the acceptable time,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 6. 2.</note> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, now is the day of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. This World is for thy Repentance, the other for thy recompence. <hi>Hic locus luctae, ille coronae. Hoc cunaeorum tempus eſt, illud corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> as Saint <hi>Chryſostome</hi> ſaith. This is the<note place="margin">Chryſ. in Heb. c. 2. Hom, 4,</note> time and place of <hi>combatting,</hi> that of <hi>crowning,</hi> this of working, that of rewarding, this for thy patience, that for thy comfort. Happie, and thrice happie are they which are thus religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly exerciſed, and Chriſtianly affected.</p>
               <p>HAPPY then by the judgement of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, is <hi>My Gracious Lord Duke</hi> (as the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of certaintie, the <hi>Lord</hi> of all, alone knoweth his) who in a comfortable Chriſtian manner was thus reſolued, and in the time of his ſhort ſickneſſe vnto his Death, piouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoted. As <hi>King Ezekiah</hi> beeing ſummoned by ſickneſſe, and the Prophets ſhort Sermon to prepare for his Death, <hi>turned</hi> preſently <hi>to the wall, prayed,</hi> and <hi>wept;</hi> ſo did this <hi>Prince,</hi> feeling his frailtie, immediately turned to the wall, prayed and wept for his former ſinnes. But
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8513:16"/> alas! Herein differed that <hi>King</hi> from this <hi>Prince,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> added vnto the dayes of <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> fifteene yeeres, but he ſhortned the dayes of <hi>Prince Lodouick</hi> in that ſame houre. Then hee Dyed in his <hi>Bed</hi> without any further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, and <hi>ſlept in the Lord with his Fathers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Kings, Princes, and Great men,</hi> who all your life long run after the dreames and ſleepe of the World, whoſe thoughts are wholy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chored vpon the Earth, and your hopes haue no further extent then the Earth, in picture of this Death, behold that the vanitie of your greatneſſe and ambition, (things ſo vaine and fraile, as when they ſeeme to gliſter, and twin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle like Diamonds) they vaniſh from our ſight, and breake themſelues in pieces like glaſſe. Your ſpirits being touched with this Death as with an Adamant, ſhould without ceaſing turne towards the firme and fixed Pole of that truth, That whatſoeuer is vnder Heauen is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but vanitie, and that the World paſſeth away with his pride and pompe.</p>
               <p>And O yee <hi>Gentlemen</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> come ſee this picture of Death, knowing of wiſe <hi>King Salomon, It is better to goe to the houſe of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>mourning, then to go to the houſe of feaſting: For that is the end of all men, and the liuing will lay it to his heart.</hi> Lay it to your heart then if you be liuing, and not ſtupid, ſenſleſſe and dead in your minde. Gaze not onely vpon it with your eyes, as little children doe vpon their painted
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8513:16"/> Booke, not learning their Leſſon, nor to your cares onely to heare of Death, nor to your tongues onely to talke of it, but lay it to your hearts, ruminate, remember, and meditate vpon Death day and night. For if yee looke vpon Death onely with your eyes, heare of it, enquire after it, and take hold of it onely with your hand, and the heart be farre from it, then it cannot auayle or profit you. The eye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the heart is a deceiuing eye, the care with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the heart is vnprofitable, the tongue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the heart is a flattering tongue, the hand without the heart is a falſe hand, and God will confound all the reſt of the bodie without the heart. Sonne giue me thy heart.</p>
               <p>Conſider the great God, who is the iudge of life and death, hath diſpoſed of the life of this <hi>Prince</hi> by ſo ſudden a <hi>Death,</hi> to the end Great <hi>Britaine</hi> ſhould know that this muſt be the end of all men: and as a man Dieth in the fauour of God, ſo without changing or recalling hee remayneth. Death being to the wicked the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils Seriant to arreſt them, and carry them without baile, vnto a Priſon of vtter darkneſſe; which to the godly is the Lords Gentleman Vſher, to conduct them to a Palace of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting happineſſe; yea Death being to the one, as Satans Cart to carry them preſently to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution in Hell, which to the other is as <hi>Elias</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Kings 2. 12.</note> his <hi>fierie Chariot</hi> to mount them vp to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:8513:17"/>
               <p>Againe, as <hi>Death</hi> is certaine, ſo the forme is vncertaine, wee ſee round figures fall otherwiſe then <hi>Cylinders</hi> or <hi>Triangles,</hi> life ends not all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one manner, the fruits of one tree fall not all at one inſtant, ſome are gathered before they bee ripe, others fall of themſelues; ſome are ſnatcht away, ſome pulled gently, and the violence of the winde and haile beateth them downe indifferently. <hi>My Lord Duke</hi> as hee liued ſo hee <hi>Died,</hi> meekely, patiently, like a Lambe; and ſo ſoone as hee felt his <hi>paine of the head</hi> increaſe, and more then heretofore, he turned his eyes towards heauen, and carried his thoughts whether his extreme griefe did conduct him. Affliction makes men forget the World, when they muſt thinke of Heauen, and it is the liuerie of the ſeruants of God.</p>
               <p>Hee prayed vnto God in his <hi>Bed,</hi> beleeuing aſſuredly, hee who is in all places where hee is called on, <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Crib, God</hi> on the <hi>Croſſe, God</hi> in the <hi>Graue,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> euery where, Who heares <hi>Ieremie</hi> in the mire, <hi>Daniel.</hi> in the Den, who makes a Palace of a Stable, of a <hi>Caluary</hi> a Paradice, makes of this <hi>Bed</hi> an <hi>Arke of propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition,</hi> and ſent his Angels thither to aſſiſt this ſoule and bring it vnto him. Hee receiues this generous, gracious, gentle, courteous and meeke Soule, which neuer refuſed his grace to any one that ſought it. That great and vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able mercy of God fortifie vs in this beleefe, and the ſame truth which recommends mercy
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8513:17"/> vnto men; for that <hi>God</hi> is all mercy, and will rather ceaſe to bee <hi>God,</hi> then to bee mercifull, who promiſeth mercy to thoſe which ſhall be mercifull.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God</hi> (it's true) might haue ſuffered this <hi>Prince</hi> to haue Died otherwiſe then <hi>ſuddenly,</hi> but his mercy had not beene ſo apparent in in any other kinde of Death, this being the ſweeteſt and eaſieſt Death, ſeeing it takes feare and apprehenſion from Death, which is <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium terribiliſsimum,</hi> moſt troubleſome. Hee calls theſe terrible and ſudden Death to the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power of his bountie, whereas man hath ſcarce the time to contribute a thought or a ſigh. And this <hi>Prince</hi> himſelfe would not end his life otherwiſe then ſuddenly, thinking it vnworthie of a great courage to languiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt a deſire of life, and the feare of Death, and to quit for the intereſt of his abode, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the vſe of a member, halfe Eyes ſight, and all his hearing, and to ſubmit himſelfe to the diſcretion of paine and old age.</p>
               <p>It is true, a <hi>ſudden Death,</hi> is terrible and fearefull to thoſe that are taken vnawares, but is not ſo to thoſe which attend it alwaies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, and who did watch, ſleepe, walke, and eate often with thoſe cogitations, made Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian like diſcourſes, &amp; ſaid ſo often, that it was not ſufficient to know the graces of God, but they muſt acknowledge them, might well bee taken, but he could not be ſurprized by Death.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8513:18"/> His deſire (you ſee) was not like vnto ours; for wee would haue wiſht to haue ſeene him ſend vp his ſoule quietly to the place of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning after a long continuance of yeeres, and that the <hi>gracious Ducheſſe his Lady</hi> had taken her laſt leaue of him; that he had giuen Legacies, and tokens to his friends and fauourites; final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appointed recompences for his old and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruants, but God thinke vs not worthie of thoſe fauours and kindneſſe of our <hi>Lord and Maſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore ſhould wee rather lament for our ſelues then for him; and let vs ſay of him as <hi>Rome</hi> did of <hi>Titus, Hee is gone for his owne good, and for our afflictions:</hi> Death which hath raiſed him to immortall felicities, doth plunge vs into a gulfe of miſeries. Wee lament iuſtly for our ſelues, who ſee our hopes Dead, and our miſeries liuing, Death hath ſtrooke but one, and hath ſlaine many. The felicitie which hee enioyes doth not eaſe the affliction which doth torment vs; the contents which he finds in heauen, takes not from vs the feeling of thoſe griefes which his abſence hath left vs vpon the earth. If Death after this blowe ſhould haue broken his bowe, deſpairing euer to make the like ſhot, that would not cure the wound which his arrow hath made. But if there be anything in this world able to mollifie our griefe, it is, that diuers nations, and many people haue ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed for that which wee lament. The affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8513:18"/> receiue ſome eaſe when as euery man beares a ſhare of their affliction.</p>
               <p>Alas! when the <hi>Doctour of Phyſike,</hi> and the <hi>Groome</hi> of his Bed-chamber, drew the Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and found him cold Dead, without breath or motion, hauing one hand lifted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heauen, and the other as is written of <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> when he was murthered in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, <hi>collecta manibus toga honeſtè cadere ſtuduit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sueton. in vita C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſ.</note> ſpread his gowne ouer himſelfe; ſo this <hi>Comely Lord,</hi> deſiring to Die decently in his <hi>Bed,</hi> (as he carried himſelfe in all his actions of his life) hee pulled vp the vpper ſheet cloſe about his necke, and ſo quietly gaue vp the Ghoſt, not ſo much as giuing one groane. Then alas! all their rubbing with hot clothes was in vaine, and to no purpoſe: when Death ſeizes one, all the <hi>Aurum potabile</hi> in the world can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not auaile nor will the <hi>Bezar ſtones</hi> helpe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the heart-beatings, nor the confection of <hi>Alchermes</hi> againſt the diſſentories, nor the feet of <hi>Elan</hi> againſt the crampes and contractions of the ſinewes. No more then <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Platoes</hi> interrogations, <hi>Gorgias</hi> his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſmes, <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> eloquence, <hi>Tullies</hi> ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, S. <hi>Thomas</hi> his fundaments, <hi>Scotus</hi> his ſubtilties, <hi>Durandus</hi> his ſentences; nor <hi>Hectors</hi> courage, <hi>Achilles</hi> his valour, <hi>Samſons</hi> ſtrength, <hi>Croeſus</hi> his riches, <hi>Caeſars</hi> fortune, can preuaile againſt Death.</p>
               <p>What pen or pencill can repreſent vnto you
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8513:19"/> the iuſt outcries of <hi>my Ladie Ducheſſe,</hi> all the houſe ouer? outcries (I confeſſe) ſo iuſtly and deſeruingly, that they may approue rather their continuance, then condemne their extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie. How ſhe caſts herſelfe vpon the ground, teared her faire haire from her head, beating her breaſt, blubbering or disfiguring her face, and renting her clothes from her backe, I am not able to expreſſe; nor yet could learned <hi>Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licarnaſſeus,</hi> who painted out the tranſported Ladies of <hi>Rome</hi> for their huſbands Death, paint out this <hi>our Ladies</hi> griefe and ſorrow.</p>
               <p>Or how ſhould I, or any other figure vnto you how the <hi>Kings Maieſtie,</hi> was amazed at the firſt dolefull newes, <hi>My Lord Duke is Dead,</hi> and euer ſince hath miſſed him. Surely <hi>Timanthes</hi> himſelfe, that inimitable painter of Mourning, if he were aliue, and would vndertake this pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of the <hi>Kings</hi> griefe, he ſhould faile in his art and skill, otherwiſe then with a vaile be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Agamemnons</hi> face. <hi>Royaltie</hi> nor <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie</hi> cannot free, nor priuiledge him from the firſt motions, and ſudden paſſions of the minde.</p>
               <p>Nor yet can I tell you how the <hi>Prince his Highneſſe,</hi> and the whole <hi>Court</hi> tooke theſe ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull newes of my <hi>Lord</hi> his <hi>Death,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then by ſilence, and by all mens teares. Diſcourſes are to no end, neither to augment the griefe of the loſſe, nor to aduance the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the glorie of this <hi>Prince</hi> LODOVICK;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8513:19"/> for the one is infinite, and the other is ſeene in his Apogea. But teares ſhew that hee which was lamented of euery man was neceſſarie for all. Teares are better vnderſtood then words, it is more eaſie to weepe for this <hi>Prince,</hi> then to ſpeake of his <hi>Princely vertues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Frame,</hi> hath ſorrowed for this <hi>Duke</hi> and <hi>Prince,</hi> like vnto a Mother who being a Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and Old hath loſt her owne ſonne, and as a Campe or an Armie of men hath loſt their <hi>Captaine</hi> and <hi>Commander.</hi> For he was borne in <hi>France,</hi> (where his wofull <hi>Mother</hi> yet liueth) and bred there vntill the ninth yeere of his age; and now Died their <hi>Captaine</hi> of an hundred <hi>men at Armes</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> of the <hi>French Kings Ordinances.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then was he in his ninth yeere brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Scotland,</hi> which now lament and grieue for his Death, as it was delighted for twenty yeers together with his life there. As alſo hee is vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſally lamented of euery one here in <hi>England,</hi> where he liued theſe twentie laſt yeeres of his life in all honor and loue, and now is <hi>Dead</hi> and <hi>Buried</hi> with great griefe and ſorrow.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ireland</hi> likewiſe ſorrow for his Death, and hang vp their Harpes from the touching or trembling of their ſtrings to any pleaſant ſound. So that his Funerall needed not any hired teares, nor borrowed weepers, called in Latine <hi>Praeficae,</hi> and in Hebrew <hi>Mekonenoth,</hi> as it is written in the ninth chapter of <hi>Ieremie,</hi> Euery
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8513:20"/> one did affoord them with abundance, thoſe which had not their eyes full of teares, had their hearts voide of pitie and commiſeration. Teares which conſtancy and grauitie held in, that they might not appeare were no leſſe bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then thoſe which common griefe did caſt forth to be ſeene. If any one had ſtrength to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt teares, it was wanting to fight with ſorrow.</p>
               <p>To tell now what the lamentation of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> was, it is impoſſible and incredible; the people ſighed and lamented one to another ſo: nor can I tell you how the poore people of the Countrie, euen ſuch as neuer ſaw him, were ſorrie for his Death, becauſe they heard of his goodneſſe. Nor yet needed he thoſe Lawes of other nations appointed to weepe at the Death of their Princes and Great men. As the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> in <hi>Diodorus</hi> Hiſtorie, wept threeſcore and<note place="margin">Diodor. lib. 2c. 2.</note> twelue dayes for the Death of their King, and we did now for our <hi>Prince</hi> LODOVICK, before his <hi>Funerall,</hi> and will many more hereafter. So did the <hi>Sparthians</hi> or <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> mourne for their <hi>Kings</hi> Death ſome certaine dayes, as <hi>Herodotus</hi> writes. Such was the cruell policie<note place="margin">Herodot. lib. 6. Ioſeph. Antiq. lib. 17. c. 8.</note> of great <hi>Herodes,</hi> to cauſe the chiefe Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of the Kingdome to bee murthered at his Death, that there might ſome teares bee ſhed then; liking belike that which <hi>Medea</hi> ſaid in the <hi>Tragedie, Mors optima est, perire</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Seneca de Med.</note> 
                  <hi>lachrymoſum ſuis,</hi> it is to bee wiſhed to bee wept for: euery man wept and lamented wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8513:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> his Death, and their teares which flowed in ſo great abundance, haue no other ſpring then the incredible bountie, goodnes, &amp; gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Neuer people ſorrowed for them that were haughtie or difficult, who haue alwaies pride in their fore-head, choler in their eyes, ſeruitude is not leſſe intolerable vnto them then Death: People flee from thoſe <hi>Princes</hi> which neuer goe out of their chambers or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces, but like Lions out of their Dennes or Cages, to feare ſome, or to hurt others. Wee ſhould neuer grieue for a ſeuere, cruel and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Prince; our teares ſhould but be fained &amp; forced; but for ſo good and milde a <hi>Prince,</hi> ſo louing to his ſeruants and followers, ſo much beloued of all, and ſo reſpected of ſtrangers, the ſorrow can neither be expreſſed nor limited.</p>
               <p>Let <hi>vs, vs</hi> aboue all others (<hi>Collegues,</hi> and <hi>Fellow-ſeruants,</hi> of one <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter</hi>) weepe, weepe and lament ſtill for the Death of our Lord: and if any man aske, or obiect vnto vs, why lament wee for which wee cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, anſwere with wiſe <hi>Solon</hi> in <hi>Laertius,</hi> wee lament becauſe our teares auaile vs not. It auailes not, to tell vs that wee lament him, not as Dead but as abſent, to repreſent vnto vs, that wee haue not loſt him, but that we expect him: wee finde occaſions daily which make vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member our loſſe, and the aſſurance of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne cannot moderate the great griefe of his Departure.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:8513:21"/>
               <p>For my part, I cannot but grieue and lament ſo long as I liue, in remembring his loue, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and liberalitie towards mee himſelfe; and how by his meanes to the <hi>Kings Maieſtie,</hi> and to <hi>my Lord of Canterburie his Grace,</hi> hee hath freed me from the neceſſitie of the world. Euen now, <hi>my heart panteth, my ſtrength faileth</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 38. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>mee: as for the light of mine eyes, it alſois gone from me,</hi> and cannot but weepe and lament, nor can I proceed any further for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor bid you fare-well. Alas!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:8513:21"/>
               <head>THE POMPOVS FVNE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RALS, OF THE GRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIOVS PRINCE, <hi>LODOVICK,</hi> Duke of <hi>Richmond,</hi> and <hi>Lenox, &amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt I would not haue you to</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 4. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>be ignorant, Brethren, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe, that yee ſorrow not, euen as others which haue no hope.</hi> Wee ſhould hope and knowe, that wee ſhall not for euer ſleepe in the graue, but wee ſhall liue with Chriſt. <hi>Many</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 12. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>that ſleepe in the Duſt, ſhall awake and riſe againe, ſome to euerlaſting life, ſome to ſhame and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall contempt.</hi> Maruell not at this (ſaid our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt,</hi> himſelfe) <hi>for the houre ſhall come,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 5. 28.</note>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:8513:22"/> 
                  <hi>in which all that are in the graues, ſhall heare his voice, and they ſhall come forth that haue done good vnto the reſurrection of life, but they that haue done euill, vnto the reſurrection of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of which wee may learne there is as great a difference betweene the <hi>Burying</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and that of <hi>Infidels,</hi> as there is a diſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the death of the Iuſt, and that of the Wicked, betweene the deceaſe of thoſe that are predeſtinated, and the exceſſe of the reprobates. Theſe die euen whiles they are aliue; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers liue, euen when they are dead: thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part hence with deſpaire; the others paſſe with hope: theſe die bodily to die immortally; the others die temporally to liue eternally: theſe ſuffer to augment their paines; the others reſt to riſe in glory.</p>
               <p>Hence alſo wee may obſerue the difference of the name, which the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> haue giuen<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>piphan haereſ. 30. Abducunt miſerum ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcentem, poſt occaſum Solis in propinquas tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas: ſepulchra, autem ſic appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantur, ſpeluncae videlicet in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris effoſae a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> conſtructae. <hi>Gen. 25. 9. Mark. 5. 2, 14. Luke 7. 12. Ioh. 19. 41.</hi>
                  </note> to their <hi>Burying place,</hi> from all others. As the <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Romanes</hi> being more ciuill then the reſt of the world did not <hi>Burne</hi> their <hi>Bodies,</hi> but <hi>Embalmed</hi> them, and <hi>Buried</hi> them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the walls of Townes and Cities, in places which they called <hi>Tumbea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Sepulchra, Spelun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas,</hi> according to the nature of place, <hi>Dennes, Tombes, Sepulchres,</hi> and ſuch: and ſince ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing receiued the gift of faith, and hope of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie, they name them <hi>Coemiteria, Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards.</hi> This name of <hi>Cemiterie,</hi> comes from
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8513:22"/> the Greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and is interpreted in our language a <hi>Dortor</hi> or <hi>Sleeping-place,</hi> grounded out of <hi>Chriſts</hi> owne words in S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> where ſpeaking of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> he ſayth, <hi>Our friend</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 11. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Lazarus ſleepeth, but I goe that I may awake him out of ſleepe,</hi> though hee addeth immediatly,<note place="margin">verſ. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Lazarus is dead.</hi> And in Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the daughter of <hi>Iairus, Prince of</hi> the<note place="margin">Matth. 9. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Synagogue, the maide is not dead but ſleepeth,</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> vſeth the ſame<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11. 30.</note> terme, <hi>and many ſleepe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All this to ſhew vnto you, that this <hi>Prince</hi> LODOVICK, <hi>Duke of Richmond and Lenox,</hi> is not Dead but <hi>Aſleepe,</hi> and that we ſhould not awake, or diſturbe him with our immoderate cryes, cares and weeping; but that <hi>Nature</hi> hauing ſhewed her dutie in teares, <hi>Reaſon</hi> now ſhould declare her pietie in performing our dutifull <hi>Exequies</hi> of his <hi>Buriall.</hi> For this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, hath euer beene commended and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in all ages, of all nations, as well of <hi>Greekes, Romans,</hi> and <hi>Barbarians,</hi> as of the ancient <hi>Iewes,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and that with all <hi>Pompe</hi> and <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie,</hi> therefore not to bee neglected of vs at this occaſion.</p>
               <p>To proue this, wee will beginne at the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,</hi> who ſhew themſelues ſuperſtitious, in <hi>Burying</hi> their Dead with great <hi>Ceremonies.</hi> As amongſt them, euen thoſe who were eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the moſt barbarous, vnciuill, and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane people; the <hi>Panebiens</hi> were very reſpectful
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:8513:23"/> in <hi>Burying</hi> their Dead <hi>honourably,</hi> placing them<note place="margin">Stob. ſerm. de Sepult. 122. Alex. ab Alex. l. 3. c. 2. Herodin Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pom. Val. Max. l. 5. c. 4.</note> in the <hi>Temples</hi> of their <hi>Gods.</hi> So were the <hi>Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> as appeared by their reſolued anſwere to <hi>Darius,</hi> King of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> that they would not ſtand out much againſt him, for their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Townes, Lands, and Poſſeſſions, but if euer he ſhould inuade the <hi>Sepulchres,</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents</hi> of their Fathers, then he ſhould know what the <hi>Scythians</hi> could doe.</p>
               <p>Other Nations of them, which ſeemed more ciuill in their carriage, were more curious in there <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of <hi>Buriall;</hi> as eſpecially the <hi>Egyptians</hi> aboue all others, in their embalming, and with ſweet Spices in preſeruing the Dead<note place="margin">Diodor. Sicul. lib 2. c. 1. Coe'. Rhodig. lib. 17. c. 20.</note> bodies from corruption, as alſo in building rich and ſumptuous <hi>Tombes,</hi> which they eſteeme of more then their beſt and honourableſt Houſes and Palaces; in mocking the <hi>Greekes,</hi> and other Nations, for building Houſes with great char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and expenſes, wherein they cannot dwell but a ſhort time; and yet they regarded not the <hi>Tombes,</hi> and <hi>Monuments</hi> of <hi>Buriall,</hi> wherein they are to reſt along time. For this cauſe were<note place="margin">Diod. Sic. l. 2. c. 5.</note> their <hi>Embalmers</hi> in great reuerence, and in no leſſe regard then their <hi>Sacrificators,</hi> dwelling with them in the <hi>Temples</hi> of their <hi>Gods.</hi> And we reade in <hi>Herodotus,</hi> it was not lawfull for<note place="margin">Herod. lib. 2. Plutarch. tract. de Iſid. &amp; O ſir.</note> them, to permit any man to be buried in wooll, more then to weare clothes of wooll in their <hi>Temples,</hi> but all muſt bee made of Linnen cloth.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:8513:23"/>
               <p>The ancient <hi>Greekes</hi> and <hi>Romanes</hi> were euer moſt curious and carefull in celebrating the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnitie of their <hi>Funerals,</hi> witneſſe <hi>Plato, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ristotle,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plat. in Phaed &amp; Cratil. Menox. &amp; lib. 4. de l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g. Ariſt. l. de virtu. &amp; Problem. ſect. 29. q. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Plutarch, Tully,</hi> and many other <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Authors, Poets,</hi> and <hi>Philoſophers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plato</hi> the beſt of the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> preſcribed a perfect Rule and gouernment, in obſeruing the <hi>Ceremonies of Burials:</hi> ſo did <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> his Diſciple in his <hi>Ethicks;</hi> and <hi>Tullius</hi> in his <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks;</hi> eſpecially <hi>Seruius</hi> in his Commentaries<note place="margin">Cic. in Top. Seru. in Aen. 6. Plutarch in vitis Theſei, &amp; The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt. <hi>aboue all in</hi> Numa.</note> vpon <hi>Virgill,</hi> commends theſe <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of <hi>Funerals,</hi> and <hi>Plutarch</hi> in all his Workes, at all occaſions, declareth how <hi>Honourable Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals are.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euripides</hi> amongſt the <hi>Greeke Poets,</hi> ſaith<note place="margin">Eurip. in Hecub. Acl. 2. Sophocl. in A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ac. &amp; Antig.</note> that <hi>Buriall is the commandement, and old Law of the Gods,</hi> and to depriue men of Buriall, is to contemne the Gods aboue and below. And <hi>Sophocles</hi> ſaith, to defraud men of their <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ceremonies</hi> of <hi>Funerals,</hi> is to violate and tranſgreſſe the <hi>Lawes</hi> of the <hi>Gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Naturally the condition of man requireth, that as it is <hi>appointed for all men once to dye;</hi> ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery-man wiſheth and requireth that this piety, humanitie and compaſſion bee ſhewen vpon him, inſuffering their dead bodies to be buried decently and honeſtly. And of this ſame natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall inclination proceedeth this great deſire, which they ſhew to haue of <hi>Burying</hi> their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, fearing leſt after their death ſome diſhonor or inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience ſhould be happen it. Such was
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8513:24"/> the ſelfe-loue of that cruell <hi>Nero</hi> towards his bodie, when hee ſaid ſurely he muſt Die, moſt<note place="margin">Suet. in Nerone.</note> inſtantly intreating that his head might not bee giuen to his Enemies. <hi>Tacitus</hi> reports of the<note place="margin">Tacit. lib. 17.</note> like of the <hi>Emperor Otho,</hi> praying that they cut not off his head, after his death, and expoſe it to the mockerie of his Souldiers. Many yeeres<note place="margin">Hom. Iliad.</note> before that, <hi>Homer</hi> bringeth <hi>Hector</hi> vanquiſhed by <hi>Achilles,</hi> inſtantly requiring, that his body be not made a prey to the Dogges, but that it may bee ranſomed, or redeemed, at what price<note place="margin">Idem ibidem.</note> he would: the ſame motion or the like, <hi>Aiax</hi> made to <hi>Iupiter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gods</hi> people both in the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi> euer religiouſly obſerued theſe <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> and <hi>Solemnities</hi> of <hi>Buriall,</hi> relying vpon their <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and that one day they ſhould liue againe, and that eternally. Yea <hi>Gods</hi> Word commands, and commends <hi>Buriall</hi> in expreſſe tearmes and practiſe. As in <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> is ſaid,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>from the Dead reſtraine it not,</hi> that is to ſay, from the <hi>Funerall Solemnitie,</hi> according to his eſtate. And ſoone after he ſaith, <hi>My ſonne powre forth</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 38. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>teares ouer the dead, and begin to mourne, as if thou haddeſt ſuffered great harme thy ſelfe, and then couer his Bodie, &amp;c. Gods</hi> owne holy Spirit<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 6. 3.</note> pronounces abſolutely, <hi>it is better to bee an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely fruit then not to bee Buried.</hi> For <hi>Practice,</hi> loc to all the ancient <hi>Patriarchs</hi> in the <hi>Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,</hi> and yet ſhall find them very diligent in theſe <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of <hi>Funerals:</hi> as <hi>Abraham,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:8513:24"/> Iſaac, Iacob, Ioſeph, Dauid, Tobie,</hi> and others.<note place="margin">Gen. 23. <hi>&amp; 49. &amp;</hi> 50. 2. Reg. 2. Tob. 14. Iohn 19. 40. Luke 23. 53. <hi>Chryſoſt. Hom. 84 in 19. chap. Ioan.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>In the <hi>New Testament,</hi> when Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt was Buried as the manner of the Iewes is,</hi> he ſignifieth ſufficiently, that <hi>Buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all</hi> was one of the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of the <hi>Law. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> was <hi>Buried honourably,</hi> and that by honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable men, his owne Diſciples; firſt to euince his owne innocencie, and to conuince the <hi>Iewes</hi> of their iniquity; ſeeing no criminall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. Hom. 4. in cap. 2. ad Hel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> perſon could be <hi>Buried,</hi> according to their owne <hi>Lawes:</hi> ſecondly it appeareth eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently by <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Nicodemus</hi> his preparation<note place="margin">Iohn 19. 37.</note> 
                  <hi>on the day of preparation,</hi> that <hi>Buriall</hi> was highly eſteemed amongſt the <hi>Iewes;</hi> in regard on that day that they might not prouide any other thing: Thirdly, hence may be collected, that it is lawfull for <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to Burie their Dead on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day, ſeeing the <hi>Iewes</hi> permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it on their <hi>Sabbath:</hi> Fourthly, that the <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall</hi> of <hi>Ieſus</hi> was the end of <hi>Iewiſh Ceremonies in Funerals,</hi> and the beginning of our <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Exequies;</hi> becauſe he would not be Buried by the ſuperſtitious <hi>Iewes,</hi> but by his owne <hi>Diſciples,</hi> who were become <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſhew, the <hi>Burying-place</hi> of <hi>Heretickes</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks;</hi> of <hi>Orthodoxalls,</hi> or of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> ſhould not bee common, more then you may obſerue there was one common place after the <hi>Buriall</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> with the <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> For <hi>Chriſt</hi> at his Death, did rent the veile of their two <hi>Religions,</hi> as hee did of the <hi>Temple,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 27. 51.</note>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:8513:25"/> and appointed <hi>Funerall Ceremonies</hi> for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, far different from the <hi>Iewiſh Superſtitions</hi> in <hi>Buriall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In conſequence of which Doctrine, Saint <hi>Luke</hi> markes expreſly, that <hi>Steuen being ſtoned,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 8. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>then certaine men fearing God, carried him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them to be buried:</hi> by thoſe of his owne profeſſion and Religion, not by <hi>Iewes,</hi> or of his contrarie part, nor yet amongſt them. So the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> who was <hi>baptized</hi> by <hi>Philip,</hi> in this<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ. 38.</hi> Dionyſ. de Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rar. Eccleſiaſt. l. 7 Hieron. Epist. 25. ad Paulam.</note> ſame Chapter, is ſaid to haue beene <hi>honourably Buried,</hi> as Saint <hi>Steuen</hi> was apparently, in that they made <hi>Magnum Planctum,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>a Magnificent Funerall</hi> for him, as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> interpretes it.</p>
               <p>It is a <hi>Chriſtian duty</hi> then, to <hi>Bury the Dead,</hi> and that <hi>Honourably</hi> and <hi>Magnificently,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meanes, honour, ranke, and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the partie defunct; howſoeuer, to <hi>Burie</hi> him decently, and with an honeſt conuoy. Saint <hi>Chryſostome</hi> renders three Reaſons why<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. Hom 4. in c. 2. ad Hebr.</note> we ſhould religiouſly <hi>Burie</hi> the <hi>Dead,</hi> and make <hi>Funerals.</hi> One is to witneſſe our reciprocall loue and charitie one towards another<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> another is to ſhew our aſſured hope of Reſurrection in others: thirdly, to be a leſſon for our owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, that as others Die, ſo ſhall we. <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantius</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lactant. lib. 6. Diuin. Institut. cap. 12. Aug. l. 1. de ciuit. Dei cap. 13.</note> ioynes the fourth, becauſe it is not fit that the Image of God ſhould be expoſed to beaſts, or rauenous fowles. Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> addeth the fifth, ſhewing our bodies are the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:8513:25"/> 
                  <hi>Tabernacle</hi> of the holy <hi>Spirit,</hi> and it were to o great an abſurditie, or foule fault to preſerue carefully the Pictures, Apparell, Iewels, and Armour of our Predeceſſours, and neglect their bodies, and bones, and their eſſentiall <hi>Spoiles</hi> of <hi>Death.</hi> Therefore wee accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the Dead to the Graue with a holy medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Death common to all, but to the faithfull a paſſage to a better life; comforting our ſelues, through aſſurance, of their happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that are gone before vs, and that we ſhall follow ſoone after them: euerie man giuing thankes vnto God for the euent of their victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, according to this ſaying of <hi>Iſaiah. The Iust are entred into peace, they reſt in their Beds, each one walking in his vprightneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence alſo is to bee obſerued, that theſe<note place="margin">Iſa. 57. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Pompes, Rites, Ceremonies,</hi> and <hi>honourable Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals</hi> in <hi>Burying the Dead,</hi> are called <hi>Iuſta</hi> in Latine; hauing nothing more frequent, among the ancient Authors, to ſignifie their actions, then thoſe Phraſes of ſpeech, <hi>Iusta facere, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta ſoluere, Iusta peragere;</hi> holding theſe duties for a principall part of <hi>Iuſtice Deſtributiue.</hi> For although the Dead feele nothing in themſelues whatſoeuer honour or diſhonour, right or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie is done vnto them, yet the Dead, (as <hi>Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pind Olymp. Odae 8. antiſtr. vlt.</note> writes) haue a right, which is due vnto them by their Parents, and Friends, euen in their <hi>Funerals</hi> and <hi>Buriall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>True, one of the puniſhments whereby <hi>God</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:8513:26"/> threatens the wicked, is that they ſhall bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of <hi>Buriall:</hi> and to <hi>Ioachim</hi> the <hi>King</hi> of<note place="margin">Ier. 22. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſrael,</hi> it was fore-told that he ſhould be buried as an <hi>Aſſe, euen drawne and caſt forth without the gates of Iſrael;</hi> and to <hi>Ieſabell</hi> that ſhee ſhould bee Buried in the bellies of dogges. And <hi>Ioſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioſeph. Antiquit. Iudaic. l. 16. c. 11</note> in the <hi>Antiquities</hi> records, that the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Herodes</hi> went to wracke and decay ſo ſoone as he violated <hi>Dauids</hi> ſumptuous <hi>Tombe,</hi> or <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 3.</note> which continued twelue hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred yeers, in honour after it was built. Both the <hi>Ciuill</hi> and <hi>Canon Lawes,</hi> haue enacted <hi>Penall Lawes</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt<note place="margin">Vlpian. l. 1. D. de Sepulchro viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Can infames 6. q. 1.</note> the tranſgreſſors in violating the <hi>Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and <hi>Burying places</hi> of the Dead; which the <hi>Ciuilian</hi> compare to the crime of Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and condemnes them by the Law of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia de vi publica,</hi> to be marked of infamie, or to bee put to death, or to bee ſent into perpetuall baniſhment, or condemned to the Mint, or Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leyes. And the <hi>Roman Oratour</hi> in his ſecond<note place="margin">Tullius lib. 2. de Legibus.</note> Booke <hi>de Legibus,</hi> cites the <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> to this purpoſe, which appointed the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in this caſe, to be tyed vnto a pillar of that <hi>Tombe</hi> or <hi>Monument,</hi> which they had broken, bruiſed, or ſpoiled any wayes; and there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine vnto death. In that ſame <hi>Booke</hi> hee tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth<note place="margin">Idem ibidem.</note> vs, that honourable Buriall is the laſt, and chiefeſt dutie woe can giue one to another.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Intereà ſocios inhumata<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> corpora terra</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Virg. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n. 11.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mandemus qui ſolus honos Acheronte ſub imo eſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:8513:26"/>
               <p>Therefore, let vs conſider more particularly how piouſly and pompouſly this <hi>Princes Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Senec. de tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quil. anim. c. 11.</note> were performed, and theſe euen by the <hi>Gracious Princeſſe,</hi> FRANCES, <hi>Ducheſſe Dowager of Richmond and Lenox,</hi> his Ladie and Wife, who after, CONCLAMATVM EST, like a <hi>Niobe,</hi> all melted in teares, Her Grace would not forget the laſt Dutie to her moſt louing Huſband; went to his Bed ſide, <note n="b" place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 7. cap. 17. Epiphan. &amp; S. Cyprian. de Sepultura Ieſu Chriſti. Virg. Aen. 4. in fine. &amp; ibi Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius etiam Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus. Cic. in Verrem. Quint. Decl. 7. Stat. papin. Epic. Val. Max. lib. 7. cap. 9. de M. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilio in fine.</note> 
                  <hi>Cloſed his eyes, ſhut</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Plutarch. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſol. ad vxo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Tibullus lib. 1. Eleg. 1. Propert. lib. 3. Eleg. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>vp his mouth,</hi> 
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Auſon. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rent. carm. 3. Suet. in Auguſt.</note> 
                  <hi>kiſſed him,</hi> and I may ſay (in ſome ſenſe) <note n="e" place="margin">Act. 9. <hi>Tert. in Apolog. Euſeb. Trig. Tur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>enſis de Pelagia.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>waſhed him</hi> (as the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; Charitable Lady <hi>Tabitha</hi> was waſhed.) I meane, ſhe <hi>Bathed</hi> him againe with her teares, cauſed him to bee <note n="f" place="margin">Tertul. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol. c. 13. pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius in Hymn.</note> 
                  <hi>Bowelled, Embalmed,</hi> and then <note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 19. <hi>Euſeb. l. 7 c. 17. Hieron epiſt. 49. Plutarch. probl. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>6. Alex. lib. 3. c. 7.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Wrapped vp in the best</hi> and <hi>finest</hi> white linnen cloth ſhee had: and all theſe piouſly, Chriſtian-like, according to the cuſtome of the Primitiue Church, and now to our Moderne vſe, of Princes and Great Men.</p>
               <p>On the next night at ten of the clocke, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie not permitting to deferre his Burying, hee was carried by his owne Seruants, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with a great number of Knights and Gentlemen vnto the Abbey Church of Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, and there in King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seuenths Chappell, (commonly called the Earle of <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> Chappell,) <hi>Honourably buried;</hi> by the Reuerend <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Lincolne, Lord keeper,</hi> &amp;c. who read himſelfe the Buriall of the Dead.</p>
               <p>Yet Her GRACE like the <hi>Goddeſſe Libitina</hi> (without offence) amongſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:8513:27"/> preſently <hi>Deſignators,</hi> three <hi>Commiſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The L. Gorge, S. Th. Sauage. S. Rob. Naper.</hi> Plutarch. Rom. probl. 13. Liuius lib. 40. &amp; 41. Budeus ad L. quicunque. Horat. 3. carm. Cocl. Rodig. l. 9. cap. 18. Val. Max. l. 5. c. 2. de L. Sylla. Plut. vbi. ſup. Budaeus Annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus in Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dect.</note> 
                  <hi>men of honor,</hi> and <hi>worthie great of reſpect,</hi> who diligently prepared for the <hi>Funeral pomps,</hi> in the ſpace of two months. In the meane time, they cauſed ſixe Roomes of <hi>Richmond Houſe</hi> to bee hung with Blackes, and the <note n="*" place="margin">L. Herodot. l. 2. Pierius hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogl. l. 40. Liuius lib. 5. Patercul. lib 11. Hom. Iliad. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Coelius l. 17. c. 19 <hi>Iſa. 57. 2.</hi> Florus lib. 4. 8. Plin. l. 35. c. 3. Tacit. lib. 3. de funere Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nici, &amp; in ſine de Iunia. Seruius in Aen. 5. <hi>Pſ. 39. 5. Pſ. 73. 20.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Effigie</hi> of <hi>My Lord his Grace,</hi> to be made, and ſet vp in the beſt chamber of the Houſe, apparelled with his Parliament Robes, lying in a blacke <hi>Veluet Bed,</hi> valanced and fringed, adorned with <hi>Scut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chions</hi> of his <hi>Armes,</hi> which they permitted all the people, at all time, that came to ſee.</p>
               <p>An <hi>Effigie,</hi> it is true, worthie to bee ſeene of all, to teach all ſtill, this life of ours is but an <hi>Image,</hi> and <hi>Aſleepe</hi> in our <hi>Bed:</hi> an <hi>Image</hi> and that neither <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (as the <hi>Greekes</hi> call thoſe that are painted vpon Tables or Boords) reall or permanent; but onely <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an apparent or vaniſhing <hi>Image,</hi> ſuch is that appeares in a <hi>Mirror.</hi> For as <hi>King Dauid</hi> knew well, and ſaid, <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but an Image aſleepe;</hi> their pompe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and glorie is but vanitie. <hi>Surely euery man in his best eſtate is altogether vanitie, Selah.</hi> or, <hi>veruntamen in Imagine pertranſit homo.</hi> And againe, As a dreame when one awaketh! <hi>O Lord, when thou raiſeſt vs vp, thou ſhalt make their image deſpiſed.</hi> And the Stoick Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher <hi>Seneca, Homo imbecillitatis exemplum, temporis ſpolium, fortunae luſus, Imago inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae.</hi> Where you may ſee that pride and pompe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:8513:27"/> of the world, eſpecially of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes,</hi> is but like a Dreame. <hi>Dauid</hi> that was a <hi>King,</hi> and knew this by experience, would teach all <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs, Emperours, Kings,</hi> and <hi>Princes,</hi> that they are but <hi>Images</hi> or <hi>Effigies,</hi> and as the Apoſtle ſaith, the <hi>Figure of the World va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7. 31.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monday,</hi> the nineteenth day of <hi>Aprill, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Herodot. l. 5. Valer. l. 1. c. 1. Solinus l. 17. Rhod. l. 18. c. 23. Strabo de Geo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>graph. lib. 17. Gregor. Turon. c. 20. &amp; 79. Rupert. l. 7. c. 20. Iuſtinian. in No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel. 123. c. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>for the Funerals; N. Quiris letho datus est: ad Exequias quibus est commodum ire, iam tempus est: Ollus ex aedibus ecfertur.</hi> That great extent of perſons &amp; honors, which proceeded, from the gate of <hi>Richmond Houſe,</hi> to that of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey- Church,</hi> may as well bee comprehended by imagination, as by diſcourſe, if we will figure to our ſelues one thouſand men in <hi>Mourning,</hi> the <hi>Chariot</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Varro de lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gua Latin. lib. 5. feſtus in verb. Indictiuum, &amp; Scal. in Caſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gat. &amp; Coniect. Alex. lib. 3. cap. 7. Gen. Dier. Terent in Phorm. act. 5. ſc. vlt. Luc. c. 7. 12. Hieron de Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la. &amp; de fabi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Virg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aen. 11. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bi. 1. de bello Ciuil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cap. 13. deſerte. Ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul de Coron. Mil. Dionyſ. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rar. Eccleſ. c. 7.</note> of <hi>Armes</hi> drawne with ſixe <hi>Horſe,</hi> wherein lay the <hi>Effigies;</hi> the <hi>Prince</hi> his <hi>Armor</hi> carried, the <hi>Sword ſheathed,</hi> the <hi>Helme creſted</hi> with the <hi>Mantelet,</hi> the <hi>Coat, Armor, Shield, Gan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Spurres,</hi> the <hi>Banners</hi> and <hi>Enſignes</hi> of <hi>Scotland, England, France</hi> (as hee had Honors in each of theſe Countries) and the <hi>Horſe</hi> of <hi>Honor,</hi> and ſeuen other led by his <hi>Gentlemen</hi> &amp; <hi>Groomes.</hi> Together with a number of * <hi>Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peters,</hi> ſounding a dolefull tone at euery turne; the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of the <hi>Kings Chappell,</hi> and of the <hi>Quire of Weſtminſter Church;</hi> and twentie <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines,</hi> of <hi>Deanes, Doctors,</hi> and others; beſides the <hi>Doctors</hi> of <hi>Phyſicke, Apothecaries</hi> and <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgians, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:8513:28"/>
               <p>After the <hi>Effigie,</hi> on an open <hi>Chariot</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed<note place="margin">Plut. Prob. 14. Val. Max. li 4. c. 1 Feſtus in verb. Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>texta. Cic. de Legib. 2. Gregor. de Niſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Epiſt. ad Olymp. Clement. Conſt. Apoſt. l. 6. c. 29. Chryſoſt. hom. 70. ad Popul. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch.</note> the <hi>chiefe Mourner,</hi> the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Lenox</hi> now is, the <hi>Defuncts Brother:</hi> aſſiſted with the <hi>Duke of Buckingham,</hi> the <hi>Marqueſſe of Hammil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Lord Steward of his Maieſties moſt Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſhold;</hi> the <hi>Lord Chamberlaine,</hi> and the moſt part of the <hi>Noble-men</hi> at the <hi>Court; My Lord Arch-biſhop of Canterbury,</hi> &amp; ſome <hi>Biſhops:</hi> Who all in ſo good an order, without any of the Marſhalſ-men, or other Vſhers, that it was maruellous to behold; the whole ſtreets being full of common people, the Windowes, Leads, and Tyles full on both ſides of the better ſort, to <hi>Westminſter Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where the <hi>Funerall Sermon</hi> was preached by <hi>My Lord Keeper,</hi> taking his <hi>Text</hi> out of the <hi>Kings</hi> thus: AND ZABVD THE SONNE<note place="margin">The Text.</note> OF NATHAN WAS PRINCIPALL OF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FICER,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1. Reg.</hi> 4. 5. at the latter end of the Verſe.</note> AND THE KINGS FRIEND. How pertinent or proper it was, iudge your ſelues. Of which I ſay truly without any feare of flattery (I hope) by any pious man, <hi>Foelix eſt cuitalis Praco contigerit, tanti meriti, tanti pecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, tanti oris, tant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> virtutis Epiſcopus,</hi> as <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> ſpake of <hi>Cyprian: happy is our dead Achilles, who, as in Heauen his ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le ſingeth praiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to God, ſo on Earth that at the interring of his body, his praiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhould be ſounded by ſuch a Reuerend Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, of ſuh worth, ſuch wiſdome, ſuch ſpeech, ſuch ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And why ſhould hee not haue praiſed him,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:8513:28"/> who was ſo Praiſe-worthy; ſeeing it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, if not commanded in the Bible. <hi>Let</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 44. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>vs now commend the famous men, and our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of whom We are begotten.</hi> This did the ancient <hi>Greekes</hi> and <hi>Latins,</hi> in time of their<note place="margin">Plato in Menox. &amp; in lib. 4. &amp; 7. de Leg. Plutar. in vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is Theſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtocl. Alex. ab Alex. Gen. dierum. l. 3. c. 7. ex Diodor. Sicolo.</note> well ruled Common-wealth, as their <hi>Hiſtories</hi> witneſſe. Not that it was lawfull for all ſort of perſons, but onely for the <hi>Nobles, Valiant,</hi> and ſuch haue <hi>well-deſerued</hi> of their <hi>Countrey</hi> in <hi>Warres,</hi> or <hi>Peace.</hi> Such they honoured, and maintained in their old age; as alſo their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren when they were decayed in their owne eſtate, and in the end commended them highly to the encouragement of others, and erected <hi>Monuments</hi> to their praiſes. <hi>Vnde Athenis in Pritaneo alebantur publicè, qui bene meriti erant de Rep. Iſque ſummus honos habebatur.</hi> This is plaine in <hi>Plato, Plutarch,</hi> and many other <hi>Greeke Authors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Amongſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> I read it was <hi>Valerius</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sueton. in Vitis Imperatorum. Liuius lib. 3. Cic. in Orat. pro Muzeur. &amp; lib. 2 de orat. Quint. in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Demonſt. Plutarch. in viti. Camilli. &amp; lib. de virtutibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lierum.</note> 
                  <hi>Poplicola,</hi> who made the firſt <hi>Funerall Oration,</hi> at the <hi>Obſequies</hi> of his <hi>companion Brutus:</hi> after him <hi>Appius Claudius, Scipion,</hi> and diuers ſince: as <hi>Augustus</hi> praiſed his <hi>Nephew. Druſus Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus</hi> at a publike Aſſembly; and <hi>Tiberius</hi> his father and ſonne; and <hi>Nero</hi> his predeceſſour <hi>Emperour Claudius.</hi> Yea it was practiſed in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of great Ladies, as <hi>Iulius</hi> made an <hi>Oration</hi> at the <hi>Funerals</hi> of his Aunt <hi>Iulia,</hi> &amp; of his Wife <hi>Cornelia;</hi> ſo did <hi>Auguſtus</hi> at his great Aunt, and <hi>Caligula</hi> at his great Aunt <hi>Liuia;</hi> and <hi>Craſſus,</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:8513:29"/> at the <hi>Exequies</hi> of his Mother <hi>Popilia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſtians haue euer beene <hi>pious</hi> in this dutie at their <hi>Funeralls,</hi> as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> in his <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hieron. ad He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>odor.</note> 
                  <hi>ad Hel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>odorum,</hi> which is, <hi>De obitu &amp; laudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Nepotiani,</hi> as a Wiſeman commends it, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>mortem ne laudes quemquam, Praiſe no man before his death,</hi> as if hee inſinued, you may praiſe after their death, but not before, leſt the praiſes be imputed vnto flatterie and lying.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Salomon,</hi> ſpeaking of a <hi>Vertuous woman</hi> ſaith, <hi>Praiſe her in the gates,</hi> that is, after ſhee is <hi>dead.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou. 31. v.</hi> vlt. Theodoret. lib. 2. cap. 14. Hiſtor. Eccleſ. lib. 9. c. 3. Hiſtor. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert. in Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor. l. 12. c. 11.</note> So <hi>Gregorie</hi> of <hi>Nice,</hi> preached a <hi>Funerall Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> vpon <hi>Melitius; Nazianzen,</hi> vpon Saint <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſile</hi> and <hi>Deſarius;</hi> and Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Funerall <hi>Sermons,</hi> for ſuch hee eſteemed Praiſe-worthy, as for the <hi>Emperours Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius, Valentinian, Gratian;</hi> and for his Brother <hi>Satirus</hi> and others, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>All which Sermons commonly tended, to declare vnto the people, how the Dead liued in honour and reputation: what dignities, offices and charges they beare in their State, how they attained vnto them, and by what degrees, of what ancient, and Noble Parents, they were borne, what ſeruices they had done vnto the <hi>King,</hi> how they were beloued of his Maieſtie, how meeke, gentle and louing they were vnto all, and of all, in their life time, and ſo lamented of all, at their <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Funerals.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of which we can haue no better patterne, nor proofe, then the explication and applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:8513:29"/> of the <hi>Reuerend Prelates</hi> and <hi>Preachers</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. King. 4. 5. <hi>vt ſupra.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Text,</hi> taken out of the firſt Booke of the <hi>Kings,</hi> approued with great applauſe, and that moſt Worthily (in my iudgement) of all that heard and vnderſtood it, as euen it is Wiſhed to bee printed, of all the judicious that heard of it. Wherein (indeed) Paralleling our <hi>Prince Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douick</hi> in euery particular with ZABVD THE SONNE OF NATHAN, WHO WAS PRINCIPALL OFFICER, AND THE KINGS FRIEND. He expreſſed abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, his Learning and Loue, towards <hi>My Lord Duke,</hi> in declaring his Chriſtian Life, and Heroick Deeds, which make me now ſpeake onely of his Death and Funerals.</p>
               <p>After whoſe <hi>Sermon,</hi> all <hi>My Lord's Armes, Armor, Standers, Banners, Shield,</hi> and <hi>Enſignes</hi> were offered by Noblemen, or by the Knights that carried them, vnto <hi>My Lord Duke of Lenox</hi> now is, who was his onely <hi>Brother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here now wee may mitigate, or temper the bitterneſſe of our affliction, with the ſweetneſſe of ſome comfort. Open your eyes <hi>Brethren</hi> of acknowledgement, you ſhall ſee the great mercy of <hi>God's Prouidence,</hi> and his ſpeciall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and care towards vs: How <hi>God</hi> is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in all his juſtices, and if of one hand hee beats vs downe, of the other hee lifts vs vp; he chuſes the time to afflict vs, when hee hath prepared to comfort vs; when apparantly hee depriues vs of all hope, yet caſts hee vs not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:8513:30"/> deſpaire. The <hi>Perſians</hi> at the Death of their <hi>King,</hi> ſmoothered, or put out all the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred flames and fire in their Houſes: but let vs (who are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi>) kindle quickly our coales of affection towards <hi>God,</hi> in taking away one <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter,</hi> to giue vs another with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay. Though <hi>God</hi> hath giuen vs check, yet not Mate, he hath ſuffered vs to ſwimme in our teares, and hearts griefe, yet hee will not haue vs to drowne in them. <hi>God</hi> hath taken vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelfe the <hi>Duke of Richmond and Lenox;</hi> but loe, he hath giuen vs a <hi>Duke of Lenox,</hi> chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in nothing but in name, as being <hi>Duke</hi> by <hi>birth,</hi> by <hi>ſucceſsion,</hi> by <hi>merite,</hi> and by all mens <hi>Wiſh,</hi> if he were to be <hi>elected.</hi> For no doubt, we ſhall find no change, no alteration, but a <hi>Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix</hi> renewed of anothers aſhes, or a <hi>Pollux</hi> that riſeth after his <hi>Brother Caſtor,</hi> to his Seruants, Tenants, and Retainers. Euen hee will proue himſelfe a truſtie <hi>Steward</hi> in <hi>Gods Houſe,</hi> of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> vnto whom it will be ſaid, as vnto his moſt <hi>faithfull Brother:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 25. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>It is well done good Steward and truſty, Thou haſt beene faithfull in a little, I will make thee ruler ouer much, enter into thy Maſters ioy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What remaines then for vs to doe more, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter</hi> is Dead, and now wee haue another aliue? Shall wee imitate the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes</hi> in theſe his <hi>Obſequies,</hi> in powring forth Bloud and Milke vpon his <hi>Tombe?</hi> Shall wee throw into the fire our beſt Iewels, and moſt
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:8513:30"/> precious things? and ſhall wee ſacrifice vnto him a Captiue? or ſhall wee bring ſome Fencers to fence and kill vpon his Graue? No ſuch <hi>Offerings</hi> and <hi>Heathen Sacrifices</hi> are to be performed of vs, nor doth the puritie and ſimplicitie of our <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> permit any ſuch ſuperſtitious <hi>Ceremonies:</hi> But wee will <hi>Offer</hi> and <hi>Sacrifice</hi> our ſelues through the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of our griefe, as ſo many <hi>Sacrifices</hi> and <hi>Victimes</hi> to his <hi>Noble Nature;</hi> wee will offer and ſhed out our teares, our ſighs, and ſobs, which are the bloud guſhing out of the wounds of our heart. Thoſe are the <hi>Funerall Honours</hi> which wee will <hi>offer</hi> to his <hi>Memorie,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member and euer ſpeake of his fauours, loue, and liberalitie towards vs. Let theſe bee his <hi>Statues, Pillars, Pyramides, Coloſſes, Obeliſques,</hi> and <hi>Triumphant Arches,</hi> which will bee more durable then all the <hi>Maruels</hi> and <hi>Monuments</hi> of <hi>Aſia,</hi> of <hi>Lidia,</hi> of <hi>Caria,</hi> of <hi>Memphis,</hi> of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> of <hi>Semiramis,</hi> of <hi>Croeſus;</hi> or of all the <hi>Marble, Maſonrie,</hi> and workes of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitecture</hi> wee can erect to his Name and Fame. For this is the Tombe and Monument which <hi>Prince</hi> LODOVICK, purchaſed and prepared for himſelfe, whiles he was aliue: and in this wee ſhall imitate <hi>Artemeſia</hi> who ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the aſhes of her husband <hi>Mauſoleus,</hi> to keepe him ſo much the better in her memorie. Finally, as his <hi>Officers</hi> brake their <hi>Staues</hi> ouer the <hi>Effigie,</hi> after all the <hi>Offerings</hi> were ended,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:8513:31"/> and the <hi>Heralds</hi> thrice proclaimed THE DVKE OF RICHMOND AND LENOX IS DEAD, with his <hi>glorious Titles</hi> of <hi>Elogie</hi> ſounded by the <hi>Trumpetters;</hi> ſo let vs ouer ſound out his praiſes of <hi>Heroicall Vertues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus as of old, they caſt into the aire a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times, <hi>Io</hi> of ioy, when any <hi>Roman Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Trimphed,</hi> or went into the <hi>Capitoll</hi> to receiue a <hi>Laurell Crowne,</hi> in ſigne and token of his <hi>Victories,</hi> before the Image of <hi>Iupiter:</hi> So now, ſeeing our <hi>Prince</hi> LODOVICK, <hi>Duke of Richmond and Lenox, &amp;c.</hi> is aſcended vp into Heauen before <hi>God,</hi> on a <hi>Chariot of Triumph,</hi> there to receiue, not a <hi>Laurell Crowne,</hi> which may fade and faile, but a <hi>Crowne</hi> of <hi>Immortall Glorie,</hi> wee ſhould all aloud cry-out, with an open mouth,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Te<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> dum procedis <hi>Io</hi> Triumphe,<note place="margin">Horat.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Non ſemel dicemus, <hi>Io</hi> Triumphe.</l>
               </q>
               <p>As he no doubt, is ſinging praiſes, with Angels and Arch-angels, vnto the Lord of Lords, and King of Kings, HALELVIAH, HALELVIAH.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:8513:31"/>
               <head>IN POMPAM FERALEM, FAELICIS PRINCIPIS, <hi>LODOVICI, Ducis</hi> Richmondiae, <hi>&amp;</hi> Lenoxiae, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> CENOTAPHIVM.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>ISTE</hi> hic etiam <hi>Viator,</hi> &amp; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ides Purpuram &amp; Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, Claritudinis Pegma, Libi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinae Trophaea? Ne mortuum hic quaeras, non querare. <hi>Cenotaphium</hi> eſt Honoris, vacuum <hi>Mortalitatis,</hi> Gloriae plenum, Memoriae ſacrarium, Pietatis pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Amoris <hi>Monumentum.</hi> Hunc Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum floridum, Fulora aurea, Culcitram va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riegatam,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:8513:32"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8513:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:8513:33"/> Tapetia conchiliata, Laquearia nitentia, Lilia ornata, Inſignia Virtutis, haec manuum decora, acroteria Pompae feralis, quae in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ita, vt in Scena minuti homines mirantur, Caelites rident, <hi>Ego</hi> nihili pendo prae choragio quo perfruor, tu ne impensè &amp; opere nimio mirere <hi>Viator.</hi> Oculos in ſublime attolle, coelum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tuere, quò me bigae albae duxerunt, <hi>PIETAS &amp; BENIGNI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAS,</hi> iſta homines, illa <hi>Deum</hi> conciliauit, vtraque ſtellatam arcem aperuit; vbi regnabo, dum <hi>Rex</hi> aetheris modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur. Interim <hi>Deum</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care pro te-ipſo, &amp; in rem tuam abi. Vale.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <p>Gentle Reader, ſeeing things out of ſeaſon are euer out of frame, and being haſtned in this, I pray thee to amend what is amiſſe in letters, words, or ſenſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8513:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:8513:34"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:8513:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:8513:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8513:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8513:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8513:36"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
